Guide to the Methodist Episcopal Church of Seneca Falls records,1851-1871.
Methodist Episcopal Church of Seneca Falls records,1851-1871
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Methodist Episcopal Church of Seneca Falls records, 1851-1871.
6007
Methodist Episcopal Church of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Minutes and subscription lists pertaining to the history and operation of the church.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
In 1812 a small class existed at Seneca Falls on the Seneca Circuit. It joined with another class at Black Brook, and by 1830 the class numbered twenty-five of whom only one was a freeholder. The group had incorporated in 1829 as the Seneca Falls Methodist Episcopal Church and had begun to build a meeting house on donated land. When work on the church stalled because of lack of money, the minister recommended abandoning the project, but members suceeded in enclosing the roof and building seats. Revival meetings were held in the structure and seventy new members were added to the congregation. In 1834 land was donated for a parsonage. In 1843-44 a portion of the congregation seceeded and organized themselves as the Wesleyan Methodist Church (Collection #6049). In 1857 the church was remodeled. In 1865 a few members left to join the Free Methodist Movement. In 1871 the old church was torn down and a new building dedicated on July 24, 1872 was constructed. In 1876 the church had 230 members and 50 probationers and 250 scholars in the Sunday School.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Minutes begin in May 1856 and end in June 1871. Contains subscription lists (1851, 1852); and minutes of quarterly meetings of the Official Board (1856-1871), which included the minister, class leaders and stewards.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Methodist Episcopal Church of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Methodist Episcopal Church--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Methodist church buildings.
Places:
Seneca County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Seneca Falls (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Minutes
  Minutes primarily concern the collection of subscriptions, the adjustment of pastor's salary, and the reports of the progress of collections. Some entries concern disciplinary cases having to do with disputes within the congregation. Items of note include:
  - Pages 3-5
    Subscription list, September 23, 1851
  - Page 6
    Subscription list, August 31, 1852
  - May 28, 1860 and February 10, 1863
    Individuals withdraw from church for various reasons.
  - July 2, 1860
    Arrangements made for a district campmeeting and a mission Sunday School in the Southwest part of the village.
  - March 10, 1860
    Decision to form anti-slavery meetings once a month.
  - July 18, 1864
    Concern over church members attending a fair.
  - n.d.
    The subject of renting or taxing the pew slips is discussed. The congregation is polled.
  - August 16, 1869 and June 10, 1871
    Preparations to repair and eventually rebuild the church.
  - April 2, 1871
    Discussion of church attendance.